A Guide to the Lilia Sofer Skala Student Portfolio, 1915-1920, 2003, n.d.
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Lilia Sofer Skala Student Portfolio, 1915-1928, 2003, n.d.
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms2003-015
1.0 cu. ft. 8 folders; 11 oversize folders
Student portfolio of Lilia Sofer Skala, who studied architecture at the University of Dresden from 1915 to 1920. Consists of her work as a student, including architectural drawings, sketches, photographs, and watercolor paintings, copies of her academic records, and other printed material.
Skala, Lilia Sofer
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The Lilia Sofer Skala Student Portfolio was donated to the International Archive of Women in Architecture in 2002. Additional materials were donated in 2004 and 2013.
Biographical Information
Lilia Sofer Skala was born in Vienna, Austria in 1896. She earned a degree in architecture from the University of Dresden and became the first female member of the Austrian Association of Engineers and Architects, practicing architecture.
Skala became a successful stage and film actress in Europe before fleeing the Nazis with her husband and two sons. Among the personal belongings with which she escaped was her portfolio of student work from the University of Dresden.
Skala immigrated to the United States in 1939 and eventually found success as an actress on Broadway and in television and film. She was nominated for an Academy Award in 1963 for her role as Mother Maria in Lilies of the Field.
Skala passed away in 1994.
Scope and Content
The collection primarily consists of Lilia Sofer Skala's work as a student of architecture at the University of Dresden from 1915 to 1920. The student work includes architectural drawings, ink and charcoal sketches, and watercolor paintings. The collection also consists of biographical information including copies of Skala's academic records, printed material about the architectural program at the University of Dresden at the turn of the century, articles by and about Skala, and press material for LiLiA!, a play about Skala written and performed by her granddaughter, Libby Skala.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into two series of Drawings and Biographical Information.
Index Terms
Subjects:
International Archives of Women in Architecture (IAWA)
Genre and Form Terms:
Photographs; watercolors (paintings)
Contents List
- Drawings, 1915-1920, n.d.
  - Construction drawings, various projects,1915-1917 (9 drawings) (Oversize Map-case 22/Drawer2/Folder 1)
  - Engineering and construction drawings, various projects,1915-1916 (10 drawings) (Oversize Map-case 22/Drawer 2/Folder 2)
  - Charcoal sketches,1915-1917, n.d. (13 original drawings and 1 photographic print) (Oversize Map-case 22/Drawer 2/Folder 3)
  - Construction drawings, various projects,1917-1920, n.d. (12 drawings) (Oversize Map-case 22/Drawer 2/Folder 4)
  - Construction drawings, Fauilieupeusiau, 1918-1919 (7 drawings) (Oversize Map-case 22/Drawer 2/Folder 5)
  - Drawings and watercolor, Putz Salon (Rauwkruist Prof. Hogg),1919-1920 (4 drawings) (Oversize Map-case 22/Drawer 2/Folder 6)
  - Construction drawings, Das Palais Einer Furstin,1920 (13 drawings) (Oversize Map-case 22/Drawer 2/Folder 7)
  - Thesis, Building Specifications for Das Palais Einer Furstin,1920 (Box-folder 1:8)
  - Construction drawings (unfinished), De Taig,n.d. (7 drawings) (Oversize Map-case 22/Drawer 2/Folder 8)
  - Pencil and watercolor sketches, Furniture for a Contest,n.d. (5 drawings) (Oversize Map-case 22/Drawer 2/Folder 9)
  - Watercolor renderings,1919-1920, n.d. (8 drawings) (Oversize Map-case 22/Drawer 2/Folder 10)
  - Ink sketches,n.d. (2 drawings) (Oversize Map-case 22/Drawer 2/Folder 11)
  - Photographs, 3 photographs of Skala's designs and 2 photographs of an orphanage in Laa, Austria for which she designed an addition/remodel (Box-folder 1:9)
- Biographical Information, 1917-1928, 2003 (Box-folder 1:1-7)
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes copies of academic records, copy of newspaper article about Skala, printed material containing information about the architectural program at the University of Dresden, articles by and about Skala (translated into English), and press material for Libby Skala's play, LiLiA!.